Hi, let us look at Masters theorem for dividing function.
안녕하세요, 함수 나누기를 위한 마스터 정리를 살펴보겠습니다.
So the Masters theorem, we take a recurrence relation in general form.
마스터 정리에서는 일반적인 형태의 점화식을 다룹니다.
So the general form of recurrence relation is
점화식의 일반적인 형태는
Tn is equals to Atn by b plus f of n.
Tn은 Atn을 b로 나눈 것에 f(n)을 더한 것입니다.
And we assume that a is greater than or equal to 1
그리고 a는 1 이상이라고 가정합니다.
means at least it must be 1
즉, 최소한 1이어야 합니다.
and b is greater than 1
그리고 b는 1보다 커야 합니다.
and f of n we say that it is of the form
그리고 f(n)은 다음과 같은 형태라고 합니다.
theta n power k log n whole to the power of p.
세타 n의 k승 로그 n의 전체 p승입니다.
We assume this is the general form.
이것이 일반적인 형태라고 가정합니다.
Now from this we will find out two values.
이제 여기서 두 가지 값을 찾아보겠습니다.
First is log a base b
첫 번째는 로그 a의 밑 b입니다.
and the second is k, k that is power of n.
두 번째는 k, 즉 n의 지수입니다.
See there are different methods here.
여기에는 여러 가지 방법이 있습니다.
Sometime we take a and b power k.
때로는 a와 b의 k승을 사용합니다.
First value is a and the next value is b power k.
첫 번째 값은 a이고 다음 값은 b의 k승입니다.
I am taking log a base b and n. This will be more easy.
저는 로그 a의 밑 b와 n을 사용합니다. 이게 더 쉽습니다.
Now based on these two values, there are three cases.
이제 이 두 값을 기반으로 세 가지 경우가 있습니다.
Case 1, if log a base b is greater than k,
케이스 1, 만약 로그 a의 밑 b가 k보다 크다면,
then answer is theta of n power log a base b.
답은 세타 n의 로그 a의 밑 b 승입니다.
So we get the answer in theta otherwise we can take big O also.
그래서 답을 세타로 얻거나 빅 오로도 사용할 수 있습니다.
This is first case.
이것이 첫 번째 경우입니다.
Case 2, if log a base b is equal to k,
케이스 2, 만약 로그 a의 밑 b가 k와 같다면,
these two are same.
이 두 값이 같습니다.
That is log a base b and power of n in function n,
즉, 로그 a의 밑 b와 함수 n의 n의 지수가
whatever the power of n in function n, both are same, equal.
함수 n의 n의 지수와 같다면, 둘 다 같습니다.
Then again it has three cases.
그러면 다시 세 가지 경우가 있습니다.
If p is greater than minus 1,
만약 p가 -1보다 크다면,
means p is not a negative,
즉, p가 음수가 아니라면,
then answer is n power k and log of p plus 1, n.
답은 n의 k승과 로그의 p+1, n입니다.
So whatever the p value is, it is raised for one more time.
그래서 p 값이 무엇이든 간에, 한 번 더 증가합니다.
Means that whole thing is multiplied by log n.
즉, 전체가 log n으로 곱해진다는 뜻입니다.
I am just writing the conditions.
조건을 쓰고 있습니다.
Mostly you find these conditions in textbooks.
대부분 이런 조건들은 교과서에서 찾을 수 있습니다.
So I am writing the conditions.
그래서 조건을 쓰고 있습니다.
Then I will take the examples and I will show you.
그 다음에 예제를 들어서 보여드리겠습니다.
If p is equal to minus 1,
p가 -1일 때,
then this is theta of n power k log of log n.
이것은 n의 k승 log log n의 세타(Theta)입니다.
And if p is less than minus 1,
그리고 p가 -1보다 작으면,
then this is theta of just n power k.
이것은 단순히 n의 k승의 세타(Theta)입니다.
We will discard log n.
log n은 버립니다.
So there are three sub cases in case 2.
그래서 케이스 2에는 세 가지 하위 케이스가 있습니다.
If these two are equal, then these are three sub cases.
이 두 가지가 같다면, 세 가지 하위 케이스가 있습니다.
Then case 3.
그 다음 케이스 3입니다.
If log a base b is less than k,
log a의 밑 b가 k보다 작으면,
then this n power k is greater.
그러면 n의 k승이 더 큽니다.
Again there are two cases here.
여기에도 두 가지 경우가 있습니다.
If p is greater than or equal to 0,
p가 0보다 크거나 같으면,
then answer is theta of n power k log n power p.
답은 n의 k승 log n의 p승의 세타(Theta)입니다.
Means as it is. Same thing.
즉, 그대로입니다. 같은 것입니다.
And if p is less than 0,
그리고 p가 0보다 작으면,
then it is big O of n power k.
그것은 n의 k승의 빅오(Big O)입니다.
Just we will take n power k and discard log n.
단순히 n의 k승을 취하고 log n은 버립니다.
That's it.
그게 전부입니다.
Now let me take some examples and show you.
이제 몇 가지 예제를 들어보겠습니다.
I will make it more simple for understanding this one through examples.
이것을 예제를 통해 더 쉽게 이해할 수 있도록 하겠습니다.
So let us solve few examples.
몇 가지 예제를 풀어봅시다.
Let us take some recurrence relation that are satisfying case 1.
케이스 1을 만족하는 몇 가지 재귀 관계를 살펴봅시다.
So Tn is equal to 2Tn by 2 plus 1.
그래서 Tn은 2Tn 나누기 2 더하기 1입니다.
What is a here?
여기서 a는 무엇입니까?
What is b here?
여기서 b는 뭐죠?
That is 2.
그건 2입니다.
What is f of n?
f(n)은 뭐죠?
This is theta of 1.
이것은 세타(Theta) 1입니다.
What is this theta of 1?
세타 1이 뭐죠?
Theta of 1 is n power 0.
세타 1은 n의 0승입니다.
Is there any log n?
로그 n이 있나요?
No, there is no log n.
아니요, 로그 n은 없습니다.
So for that also I will take log power 0.
그래서 그것도 로그 0승으로 취할 겁니다.
See, this one is n power 0 and log n power 0 also.
보세요, 이것은 n의 0승이고 로그 n의 0승도 마찬가지입니다.
Both are 0.
둘 다 0입니다.
Now from this, I will find out log a base b and n power k.
이제 여기서 로그 a 밑 b와 n의 k승을 찾을 겁니다.
So what is k here?
여기서 k는 뭐죠?
k is 0.
k는 0입니다.
So k is 0 and p is also 0.
그래서 k는 0이고 p도 0입니다.
So what is log a base b?
로그 a 밑 b는 뭐죠?
Log 2 base 2 is 1 and k is 0.
로그 2 밑 2는 1이고 k는 0입니다.
See, log a base b is greater than k.
보세요, 로그 a 밑 b가 k보다 큽니다.
This satisfies first condition k is 1.
이것은 첫 번째 조건을 만족합니다. k는 1입니다.
What is that answer I have to write?
제가 써야 할 답은 뭐죠?
The answer I have to write is theta of n power log a base b.
제가 써야 할 답은 세타 n의 로그 a 밑 b 승입니다.
Log a base b is what? 1.
로그 a 밑 b는 뭐죠? 1입니다.
So n power 1.
그래서 n의 1승입니다.
That is it.
그게 전부입니다.
Second example.
두 번째 예제입니다.
Tn is equal to 4Tn by 2 plus n.
Tn은 4Tn 나누기 2 더하기 n입니다.
So directly I will find out these two.
그래서 직접 이 두 가지를 찾을 겁니다.
Log 4 base 2 is what? 2.
로그 4 밑 2는 뭐죠? 2입니다.
Log a base b I found out directly.
로그 a 밑 b를 직접 찾았습니다.
Instead of finding out a and b and then p,
a와 b를 찾고 나서 p를 찾는 대신에,
I have directly found out this one.
이것을 직접 찾아냈습니다.
So what is the k? n power is what? 1.
그래서 k는 무엇인가요? n의 지수는 무엇인가요? 1입니다.
What is the p? That is 0.
p는 무엇인가요? 그것은 0입니다.
So this satisfies which case?
그래서 이것은 어떤 경우를 만족하나요?
This is 2 greater than 1.
이것은 2가 1보다 큽니다.
So it comes under case 1.
그래서 이것은 경우 1에 해당합니다.
So theta of n power log a base b.
그래서 theta(n의 log a base b).
So theta of n power 2.
그래서 theta(n의 2제곱).
Now third example for the same case 1.
이제 같은 경우 1의 세 번째 예제입니다.
Tn is equal to 8Tn by 2 plus n.
Tn은 8Tn/2 더하기 n입니다.
Log 8 base 2 is 3.
log 8 base 2는 3입니다.
n power k is k is 1.
n의 지수 k는 1입니다.
So 3 is greater.
그래서 3이 더 큽니다.
So this is theta of n power 3.
그래서 이것은 theta(n의 3제곱)입니다.
That's it.
그게 다입니다.
8 base 2 is 3 and this is 1 only.
8 base 2는 3이고 이것은 1입니다.
Now look at this.
이제 이것을 보세요.
If the recurrence relation is Tn 8Tn by 2 plus n square.
재귀 관계가 Tn 8Tn/2 더하기 n 제곱이라면.
So k is 2.
그래서 k는 2입니다.
There is no p here, p is 0.
여기에는 p가 없고, p는 0입니다.
There is no log n here.
여기에는 log n이 없습니다.
So in simple words you find out this and this
그래서 간단히 말해서 이것과 이것을 찾아내고
and find out log.
log를 찾아내세요.
n power of n you see.
n의 지수를 보세요.
So power of n is 2.
그래서 n의 지수는 2입니다.
This is 3.
이것은 3입니다.
So still this is greater.
그래서 여전히 이것이 더 큽니다.
So answer is n power 3.
그래서 답은 n의 3제곱입니다.
Let me change.
변경해 보겠습니다.
Tn is equal to 9Tn by 3 plus 1.
Tn은 9Tn 나누기 3 더하기 1입니다.
What is log 9 base 3?
로그 9의 밑이 3은 무엇인가요?
This is 2.
이것은 2입니다.
What is k?
k는 무엇인가요?
This is what?
이것은 무엇인가요?
n power 0.
n의 0승입니다.
This is n power 0.
이것은 n의 0승입니다.
k is 0.
k는 0입니다.
So this is greater.
그래서 이것이 더 큽니다.
This is greater.
이것이 더 큽니다.
So the answer is theta of n power this one 2.
그래서 답은 n의 2승의 세타입니다.
If this is n.
만약 이것이 n이라면,
n power 1.
n의 1승입니다.
This is greater.
이것이 더 큽니다.
So again n square only.
그래서 다시 n 제곱입니다.
If this is 2 then this is 2.
만약 이것이 2라면 이것도 2입니다.
So this is not greater.
그래서 이것은 더 크지 않습니다.
They are equal.
그들은 같습니다.
So they come under case 2.
그래서 그들은 케이스 2에 속합니다.
So as long as this is greater
그래서 이것이 더 큰 한
whatever the result you are getting directly put it here.
당신이 직접 얻는 결과를 여기에 넣으세요.
Let us quickly look at some examples.
몇 가지 예를 빠르게 살펴봅시다.
Suppose this is 4n by 2 and this is n.
예를 들어, 이것이 4n 나누기 2이고 이것이 n입니다.
What is this 4 base 2?
이것은 4의 밑이 2는 무엇인가요?
Log 4 base 2?
로그 4의 밑이 2는?
2.
2입니다.
And this is 1.
그리고 이것은 1입니다.
So answer will be theta of n square only.
그래서 답은 n 제곱의 세타입니다.
If this is 8.
만약 이것이 8이라면,
8 base 2.
8의 밑이 2입니다.
Q.
Q.
This is 1 only.
이것은 1입니다.
So this will be Q.
그래서 이것은 Q입니다.
If you have 8 here.
여기에 8이 있다면.
And here it is n log n.
여기에는 n log n입니다.
So just we see power of n.
그래서 우리는 n의 거듭제곱을 봅니다.
n power k.
n의 거듭제곱 k.
k you check.
k를 확인하세요.
So this is 1.
그래서 이것은 1입니다.
This is 8 base 2.
이것은 8의 밑이 2입니다.
3.
3.
So this is greater.
그래서 이것이 더 큽니다.
As long as log a base b is greater than power of n.
로그 a의 밑 b가 n의 거듭제곱보다 크면,
Power of n in function f of n.
함수 f(n)에서 n의 거듭제곱.
We take log a base b only.
우리는 로그 a의 밑 b만 취합니다.
Alright.
알겠습니다.
Next we will look at second case.
다음으로 두 번째 경우를 보겠습니다.
Tn is equals to 2tn by 2 plus n.
Tn은 2Tn/2 더하기 n입니다.
Log 2 base 2 is 1.
로그 2의 밑 2는 1입니다.
And k is 1.
그리고 k는 1입니다.
So this is.
그래서 이것은.
They are equal.
같습니다.
Then what is the p here?
여기서 p는 무엇입니까?
There is no log n.
로그 n이 없습니다.
So p is 0.
그래서 p는 0입니다.
P is 0.
p는 0입니다.
Right?
맞죠?
So this is p is greater than minus 1.
그래서 이것은 p가 -1보다 큽니다.
So what it should be?
그래서 어떻게 되어야 할까요?
n power k and log p plus 1.
n의 거듭제곱 k와 로그 p 더하기 1.
So whatever n is.
그래서 n이 무엇이든 간에.
n log n.
n 로그 n.
So p was 0.
그래서 p는 0이었어요.
So I made it as 1.
그래서 1로 만들었어요.
Now in simple terms I will explain you.
이제 간단히 설명할게요.
Just watch this.
이것만 보세요.
Don't look at this one.
이건 보지 마세요.
Right?
알겠죠?
Later you can look at.
나중에 보셔도 돼요.
You can pause and rewind and you can go through this one.
멈추고 되감아서 보실 수 있어요.
So simply I will explain this one.
그래서 간단히 설명할게요.
Look at this.
이걸 보세요.
2 base 2 is 1.
2의 2제곱은 1이에요.
n power is 1.
n의 지수는 1이에요.
So whatever f of n is.
그래서 f(n)이 무엇이든 간에.
Multiplied by log n.
로그 n을 곱해요.
Simple.
간단하죠.
N of p.
N의 p.
Right?
맞죠?
This is what we found in the book.
이게 책에서 찾은 거예요.
So unless I show this.
그래서 이걸 보여주지 않으면.
You may not feel that I am showing Master's Theorem.
제가 마스터 정리(Master's Theorem)를 보여주고 있다는 느낌이 안 들 거예요.
That is the reason I have written it.
그래서 이렇게 썼어요.
Okay?
알겠죠?
It can be made more simple.
더 간단하게 만들 수 있어요.
So watch this one.
이걸 보세요.
Now if this is 4 by 2 and n square.
이제 이게 4 나누기 2이고 n 제곱이라면.
This is 4 by 2 is what?
이게 4 나누기 2는 뭐죠?
2.
2죠.
k is how much?
k는 얼마죠?
Both are same.
2.
So what I should do?
그래서 어떻게 해야 하나요?
n square log n.
n 제곱 로그 n.
This is the answer.
이게 답입니다.
If suppose already I have log n.
만약 이미 로그 n이 있다면,
So again you multiply by log n.
다시 로그 n을 곱하세요.
So log square n.
그래서 로그 제곱 n.
n square log n.
n 제곱 로그 n.
So multiply by n square log n again.
그래서 다시 n 제곱 로그 n을 곱하세요.
If suppose already this is n square log n.
만약 이미 n 제곱 로그 n이라면,
So make it as log cubed.
로그 세 제곱으로 만드세요.
So it means when these two are equal.
그래서 이 둘이 같을 때를 의미합니다.
Log n base b and n power.
로그 n 밑 b와 n의 거듭제곱.
Not log.
로그가 아닙니다.
n power is same.
n의 거듭제곱이 같습니다.
Then take this as it is multiplied by log n.
그러면 이것을 그대로 두고 로그 n을 곱하세요.
Right?
맞죠?
Take this as it is and multiply by log n.
이것을 그대로 두고 로그 n을 곱하세요.
Suppose this is log power 5.
만약 이것이 로그 5제곱이라면,
Make it 6.
6으로 만드세요.
Now I will write few more.
이제 몇 가지 더 써보겠습니다.
See.
보세요.
8 log base 2 and n cube.
8 로그 밑 2와 n 세제곱.
So what is this?
그래서 이게 뭐죠?
8 base 2 is what?
8 밑 2는 뭐죠?
3.
3.
What is n power k?
n의 거듭제곱 k는 뭐죠?
n power k.
n의 거듭제곱 k.
k is what?
k는 뭐죠?
3.
3.
Both are equal.
둘 다 같습니다.
3, 3.
3, 3.
So the answer is what?
그래서 답은 무엇일까요?
n power 3.
n의 3제곱입니다.
Log n.
로그 n.
Take that n power 3.
n의 3제곱을 가져가세요.
Whatever f of n is.
f(n)이 무엇이든지 간에.
Multiplied by log n.
로그 n을 곱하세요.
That's it.
그게 전부입니다.
This is case 2.
이것이 케이스 2입니다.
In that first one I have shown you.
첫 번째로 보여드린 것입니다.
Now I suppose the recurrence relation is like this.
이제 재귀 관계가 이렇게 되어 있다고 가정해봅시다.
2 t n by 2 plus n by log n.
2 t n/2 더하기 n/로그 n.
Then all the 2 base 2 is 1.
그러면 모든 2의 밑은 1입니다.
k power power of n is 1.
k의 n 제곱은 1입니다.
k is 1.
k는 1입니다.
But what is the p value?
하지만 p 값은 무엇일까요?
p is, this is in denominator.
p는, 이것은 분모에 있습니다.
So it is minus 1.
그래서 -1입니다.
Then what I should do?
그럼 어떻게 해야 할까요?
I told you that if these 2 are equal.
제가 말씀드렸듯이 이 두 값이 같다면.
They are same.
같습니다.
This is 1.
이것은 1입니다.
Then directly take f of n and multiply it by log n.
그럼 직접적으로 f(n)을 가져와서 로그 n을 곱하세요.
If I do that then log n log n gets cancelled.
그렇게 하면 로그 n 로그 n이 상쇄됩니다.
No, don't do that.
아니요, 그렇게 하지 마세요.
Here the method is little different.
여기서는 방법이 조금 다릅니다.
So take it as theta of n as it is.
그래서 그냥 n의 세타(Theta)로 받아들이세요.
Instead of log n make it as log of log n.
log n 대신 log의 log n으로 바꾸세요.
This is the answer.
이게 답입니다.
This is what this method says.
이 방법이 말하는 바입니다.
If it is equal to minus 1.
만약 그것이 -1이라면,
So p is minus 1.
그래서 p는 -1입니다.
So this I can write it as into log minus 1 n.
그래서 이것을 log -1 n으로 쓸 수 있습니다.
So this one.
그래서 이것입니다.
And even in the same situation.
그리고 같은 상황에서도,
If this is denominator is log square n.
만약 분모가 log 제곱 n이라면,
Then this will be into log minus 2 n.
그러면 이것은 log -2 n이 됩니다.
So this will be too small.
그래서 이것은 너무 작아질 것입니다.
This will be too small.
이것은 너무 작아질 것입니다.
Minus 2.
-2입니다.
Right?
맞죠?
Then in this case it is less than minus 1.
이 경우에는 -1보다 작습니다.
Less than minus 1.
-1보다 작습니다.
So in that case don't take this log of log n also.
그런 경우에는 log의 log n도 취하지 마세요.
Don't take log of log n also.
log의 log n도 취하지 마세요.
That is power 2 power 3 something.
그것은 2의 거듭제곱, 3의 거듭제곱 같은 것입니다.
Then ignore it.
그럼 무시하세요.
Just take this one.
그냥 이것만 취하세요.
That's all.
그게 다입니다.
Right?
맞죠?
These are the 3 sub cases in case 2.
이것들이 케이스 2의 3가지 하위 케이스입니다.
The third case I will show you.
세 번째 케이스를 보여드리겠습니다.
Tn is equal to Tn by 2 plus n square.
Tn은 Tn/2 더하기 n 제곱입니다.
What is A base B?
A의 밑 B는 무엇입니까?
Log 1 base 2 is 0.
log 1의 밑 2는 0입니다.
And k is 2.
그리고 k는 2입니다.
So this is smaller than this one.
그래서 이게 이거보다 작습니다.
This is greater.
이게 더 큽니다.
So this is theta of n square.
그래서 이건 n 제곱의 세타(Theta)입니다.
Theta of n square.
n 제곱의 세타(Theta)입니다.
Right?
맞죠?
If this is 2 base 2.
만약 이게 2 밑 2라면.
2 base 2 is 1.
2 밑 2는 1입니다.
Still this is greater.
그래도 이게 더 큽니다.
Answer is n square.
답은 n 제곱입니다.
And if suppose this is having log n.
그리고 만약 이게 로그 n을 가지고 있다면.
Then take log n as it is.
그냥 로그 n을 그대로 가져가세요.
If you are having log square n, take log square n as it is.
로그 제곱 n이 있다면, 로그 제곱 n을 그대로 가져가세요.
Whatever it is, you take this one.
어떤 것이든 이걸 가져가세요.
Power of n is greater than this log A base B.
n의 지수가 이 로그 A 밑 B보다 큽니다.
So take directly f of n.
그래서 직접적으로 f(n)을 가져가세요.
It is very simple.
아주 간단합니다.
Take f of n.
f(n)을 가져가세요.
This is f of n only.
이건 f(n)만입니다.
Power of k is greater than directly take it.
k의 지수가 더 크면 직접 가져가세요.
Okay?
알겠죠?
n square log square n.
n 제곱 로그 제곱 n.
That is already directly have taken it.
그건 이미 직접 가져갔습니다.
Okay?
알겠죠?
Then, if this is suppose 4n by 2 and this is 3.
그럼, 만약 이게 4n 나누기 2이고 이게 3이라면.
So this is a 2 you see and this is a 3.
그래서 이건 2이고 이건 3입니다.
So the answer is n cube.
그래서 답은 n 세제곱입니다.
That is greater.
그게 더 큽니다.
So whatever it is along with that if you have log also you take it.
그래서 어떤 것이든 로그가 함께 있다면 그것도 가져가세요.
But one thing.
하지만 한 가지.
If that is having log in the denominator.
만약 로그가 분모에 있다면.
But this is greater.
하지만 이게 더 큽니다.
So don't take the denominator.
그래서 분모는 취하지 마세요.
Just take n power 3.
그냥 n의 3제곱만 취하세요.
That's it.
그게 다입니다.
Right?
맞죠?
These are the cases and I have shown with some examples.
이것들이 그 경우들이고, 몇 가지 예시로 보여드렸습니다.